[Music]
alone
inexperienced life has never been
tougher for this young
Aang she will have to go to
extraordinary lengths to find enough
food
a third of her kind will fall and break
bones or
worse in this hostile World Only the
strongest make it to the top
[Music]
torrential rain tropical heat and the
Relentless assault of
insects if you you're not prepared the
jungle will eat you
alive but these conditions have created
a home for more species than anywhere
else on the
planet you might think it's an animal
[Music]
Eden but it's more like a wildlife war
zone now that the rains the lifeblood of
these extraordinary worlds are becoming
more
unpredictable the battle for survival
has never been fiercer
even rainforests have dry
seasons Rivers become the focus of
jungle life
a
Jaguar South America's apex
[Music]
predator Jaguars will hunt
anything from a
vouer to an anaconda
but nothing's guaranteed
it's been days since she's
[Music]
eaten Jaguars are the most aquatic of
all big
cats she'll have more success in the
water
capy
bar a big opportunity
there are other
[Applause]
options but there's also
competition a
male he's h Ed here for over a decade
taking on dangerous
prey and other
[Music]
Jaguars life here isn't getting any
easier as dry seasons become more
extreme competition for prey increases
better for her to hunt in less contested
Waters where prehistoric Killers love
waiting to drag their victims
under with each
step a trap could snap shut
with the right bite
she'll Pierce skull and immobilize
[Applause]
it but this Cayman is much more than a
mouthful
[Music]
a kill this big has rarely been
recorded it will feed her for
days for other animals finding food at
the height of the dry season is much
more of a struggle
fruit makes up around 60% of this young
or's
diet to survive she must form a complex
mental map of where and when to find
it this takes years
[Music]
up here there's nothing but
leaves rainfall has dropped by a third
and droughts are more
frequent how can she predict where to
find food when the world around her
keeps
changing the more She
searches the more she risks
[Music]
Far
Below on the forest
floor only 2% of sunlight
penetrates it's not water that limits
life it's
light for every 100,000 seeds only one
will
survive fewer still will ever reach the
canopy they have to fight for their
place in the
sun just half an inch can mean the
difference between
life and death
each plant has its own strategy to get
ahead this struggle makes the jungle one
of the most competitive environments on
earth a war in which every leaf
matters in the dry season there's not
much else to
eat plants fight back with spikes and
[Music]
poison loading their leaves with toxin
with each fight their victims become
sicker and
sicker there is an
antidote but to reach
it they must face the jungle's most
dangerous predators
poisoned by the plants they eat these
animals must reach the
antidote but it's a Dangerous
Mission
ocelot
[Music]
jaguas and Puma are
waiting a deadly game of hide and
seek and at its heart
a most unlikely
cure
clay it's rich in the minerals and salts
needed to neutralize the
toxins but the longer the dry
season the more they must visit the clay
[Music]
with so much Danger on the forest
floor it pays to keep off the ground
this arang spends 90% of her time in the
[Music]
trees as the heaviest arboreal species
in the world orangs let their weight do
the work
[Music]
tree swaying saves half the energy she
would normally use to
[Music]
climb shortage of food in the dry season
forces her to rest
[Music]
more each afternoon she makes her bed
weaving branches into a nest that will
keep us safe through the
[Music]
night and these trees provide more than
food and shelter
[Music]
remarkably they also help create the
jungle's
weather by the end of the dry season the
sun is at its most
intense trees pump out more water vapor
than at any other time of
year in this jungle almost 20 billion
tons every
day all this water creates the wet
season
here but this jungle is shrinking and
its rain making power is
[Music]
fading every
decade the change from dry to wet comes
a week later
a mighty storm is
brewing but before it strikes there's a
killing to be made
competition for food is so intense
during the
[Music]
day it has forced some
creatures into the
[Music]
night spectral R
tarus to thrive in the dark they've
evolved eyes bigger than their
brains and the best tonight vision of
any
primate but they still need a little
help a
moon when it's
full this family can catch
more so they hunt for twice as long
[Music]
but when storm clouds obscure the
[Applause]
moon others are better equipped to kill
in the
shadows this python sees with
heat and smells with taste
the tables turn
again living in a group means these
tarus can look out for each other
[Music]
with no element of
surprise the python has no chance
but life is about to get
tougher the wet season has
arrived and it's hitting harder than
ever
before the wet season
breaks there are more lightning strikes
in jungles than anywhere else on
Earth by 2050 some estimate they will
increase by a third
the storms these trees help
create can also be their downfall
[Applause]
the death of an emergent tree is an
essential part of the cycle of
Life The increased humidity during the
wet
season sets off a chain
[Music]
reaction fungi and slime molds raced to
decompose dead matter on the forest
floor
rotten Decay run
rampant faster than anywhere else on
Earth in some jungles species of fungi
outnumber plants 33 to
1 as they feed on the dead they recycle
critical nutrients which the forest uses
to grow
many spread by releasing
spores up to 30,000 a
second if just one of these spores lands
in the right place and takes
root it can colonize a whole new
area but not all fungi feed on the Dead
days ago a SPO landed on this
ant now she's acting
strange a network of roots has
infiltrated her
muscles her body has been taken over by
cord
deeps a parasitic fungus
it floods her brain with
chemicals drugging
her compelling her to head where
conditions are
perfect just the right amount of light
just the right amount of humidity
for the parasite growing
inside it forces her to clamp down in a
death bite and ceps reveals its gruesome
nature
[Music]
after 3 weeks of
growth cceps can release its own
spores infecting more
ants releasing more
spores infecting more ants releasing
more spores infecting more an infecting
more an
more and more and
more ceps can wipe out entire ant
[Music]
colonies but more than just answer at
risk
there are over 600 species of ceps
spread across the
world most are found in
jungles where they prey on a whole host
of victims
[Music]
the wet season brings a flush of fruit
to the
[Music]
canopy L Gibbons must move fast before
it's all gone
they fly through the trees at 35 M
hour even with a baby on
board they can cover 40 ft to a single
leap but they don't get it right every
time this family of lar Gibbons lives in
a dangerous
World their Forest is being
fragmented one day they may face a
jump they can't quite make
food is harder to find as a wet season
grows more
erratic and when the rain comes it can
fall in shorter more intense
bursts if it's too
wet it's best to sit
tight this arang has leared a lot from
her
mother how to make a jungle
umbrella it comes in handy in the
rainiest environment on
Earth for many animals heavy rain stops
activity
but for some that's not an
option this male booted racket tail
humming bird lives on the brink of
starvation just two hour hours without
nectar and he could
die hummingbirds have the fastest
metabolisms on
Earth some need to visit 2,000 flowers a
day just to keep
going this mountainous Forest is one of
the few jungles that is getting wor
wet Heavy Rain is predicted to increase
and when you weigh less than a
nickel raindrops are a bombardment
water logged feathers slow his
progress staying Airborne becomes more
demanding but he's running on
empty and the clock is
ticking even during a downpour
competition for flowers is
fierce a buff tailed
Coronet intent on keeping the nectar
filled flowers for
himself the racket tail is no
competition for the Coronet
he must wait for another
[Music]
opportunity as the raid slow over 40
species fight for their neck to hit
[Music]
with the Coronet facing bigger
battles this is a racket Tail's
chance to sneaker
[Music]
SI it takes more energy to hover than
almost any other activity on Earth we'd
have to drink over a can of soda a
minute to keep
up another racket
tail evenly matched he won't back
[Music]
down tail
Spade feet
forward he means business
[Music]
The Winner Takes
all but he can't
rest he still has a lot of flowers to
visit and the next downpour is never far
[Music]
off raain fall in the Andes transforms
life over a thousand miles
away so much water collects in the
Amazon basin below that the Earth's
crust sinks by 3 in
a drowned
Forest this extreme change takes
months even so it can creep up on those
who live their life in slow motion
[Music]
moving between the trees becomes
challenging she needs to find her next
meal but she's
surrounded creatures that spend most of
the year on the forest
floor now find themselves floating 30 ft
above
it their only Refuge is in the
trees but she must Brave the Deep
this sloth's home is
flooded to find her food she must
swim defenseless against What Lies
Beneath
[Music]
like most animals here sloths are
adapted to get through this annual
flood fermenting leaves fill her stomach
with
gas that helps keep her
afloat she's three times faster in water
than on land
[Music]
when the forest
floods it opens up a whole new
[Music]
world pink river dolphins can explore an
area larger than Arizona
they echolocate to hunt for fish in the
Merk using higher frequencies than their
Marine
cousins to see with superior
[Music]
definition recently these floods have
been reaching record-breaking highs
but there have also been devastating
lows and as our world changes drought is
the greatest natural threat to jungles
worldwide Australia was once covered by
a jungle larger than the Amazon
rainforest now barely 1%
survives clinging to what little water
[Music]
remains and little red flying foxes
cling on with
it it's a 104
F just 4° more and this male will die of
heat
shock he needs to escape the
[Music]
Sun but with hundreds of thousands of
bats in the colony the shadiest spots a
hard one
[Music]
exposed he's dangerously
dehydrating the river is their only
[Music]
salvation but it can also be their
ruin these waters are
infested freshwater crocodiles
better to stay
away try and hold out till
Nightfall but with every breath he loses
more
[Music]
water more and more bats give in their
thirst and he won't last much
longer it's safer to share the
risk to collect water they must dip
their fur in the
river but no one wants to be first
[Music]
safe but he must Brave this River every
day until the rains
arrive over the next 50 years it could
get too hot and dry for this colony to
survive at
[Music]
all could this be the future for jungles
around the world
[Music]
these amazing forests not only create
oxygen and rain that nourish our planet
they're also home to a greater diversity
of animals than anywhere else on
Earth these creatures are super
specialized to survive all the
complexities of life in the jungle but
in times of change
that also leaves them highly
vulnerable it takes years for Nang to
learn how to find its way in these
[Music]
forests and today's changing climate
makes life even
[Music]
tougher and that is an all she has to
contend with
[Music]
rainforests around the world are
disappearing faster than ever
before her future
like that of all jungle
life has never been less certain
[Music]